<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the Solemne League and Covenant, proving it to be obligatory. Together with a treatise concerning oathes, and particularly the obligation of forced oathes. By an Episcopall divine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81962</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867018</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119308</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240925939</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1055_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208010</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867018</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867018e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119308)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1055[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the Solemne League and Covenant, proving it to be obligatory. Together with a treatise concerning oathes, and particularly the obligation of forced oathes. By an Episcopall divine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: J.D.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 19. 1660"; the second 1 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119308:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning The Solemne League And COVENANT, Proving it to be Obligatory.</p>
            <p>Together with a TREATISE Concerning OATHES, And particularly The Obligation of forced Oathes.</p>
            <p>By an <hi>Episcopall</hi> Divine.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119308:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119308:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>John</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Excester</hi> his Grace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S well the consideration of your Lordships most eminent dignity in the Church, as those evident and publick testimonies of your pious affection to it, which you have not ceased at those times to demonstrate, when the black clouds of Malignity had overspread it; hath emboldened me to present this Treatise to your Patronage. Nor can I doubt that your Lordship, who hath been so high a Vindicator of the Churches honour, will deny to Cherish with the beames of affection, any thing which offers at the defence of Devotion and Piety. Blessed be God, the Sun of the Gospel hath again appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the truth of Religion in part dispell'd, those clouds which so lately hid it in obscurity: how great an Instrument your Lordship hath been in the promotion of this great and happy work, is fitter to be left to the judgment of the world, then for me to speak or your Lordship to hear. But that
<pb facs="tcp:119308:3"/>there are still some mists in this our Hemisphere, whose foggy influence doth blind wages of truth, is so well known and so much lamented by your Lordship that I dare be bold to assure my self, that you will look upon nothing as needless or unneces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary which indevours to make plain the Catholick paths. The thing it self was long since delivered in Latin, by a worthy and pious Divine in order to the satisfaction of a learned Auditory; under your Patronage and Protection my Lord, it offers it self in English for the vulgars devotion and reasonable service. Let your Lordship therefore be gratiously pleased, to excuse the boldness of this address, and to put it on the score of our holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church, who hath already been so signally obliged by your endevours; and grant that he who continually prays both for Her &amp; Your Lordships prosperity, may confidently assume the boldness to subscribe himself</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(My Lord)</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>Your most humble and<lb/> most Obedient Servant,<lb/> J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119308:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the Solemne League and Covenant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is evident to any considering man, that the Dispute of the Present, and, if it doth not please God mercifully to prevent it, the Quarrel of the succeeding Age, will be upon these two Heads, <hi>viz. Ceremonies,</hi> whether they may lawfully be observed; and the <hi>Covenant,</hi> whether it may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be broken. Concerning the First of these, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from <hi>Reasons of Scripture</hi> against, and those ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Reason of State</hi> for them, are so directly thwarting and contradictory to each other, that hitherto it hath been a kind of drawn match between <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Policy:</hi> and the Truth of the Question, as to the concernements of <hi>Christian Liberty,</hi> by the Irreligious and Unpeaceable proceeding of too many, hath given so great scandall, that whoever Disputes for the <hi>Power of Impositions,</hi> although in farre greater matters than those contested about, will have a very great advantage against a modest Opponent: Since though the Principle, upon which the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> do ground their Dissent, <hi>viz. That Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Things in Religious Worship, ought not to be made Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,</hi> may for Reasons obvious enough, easily be asserted, yet the Consequences, which have resulted from the Intemperate Abuse of it, are too Manifest, to be denied and too Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to be defended. And therefore in the midst of so many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119308:4"/>
               <hi>offences</hi> most impiously given, and but too justly taken, it cannot but be looked upon, as a Singular Goodnesse of God, that his <hi>Majesty</hi> hath already indulged so farre; whose Pious Concessions, had they been as Candidly pursued, as they are by his <hi>Majesty</hi> most Christianly pressed, that Controversie had ere this been ended. For while men, in these Circumstances of Worship, were left free to the Guidance of their several Perswasions, a short time would have decided whether <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony</hi> or <hi>substance;</hi> the <hi>Forme</hi> or the <hi>Power</hi> of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, would most prevaile amongst Conscientious Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours.</p>
            <p>But since notwithstanding his <hi>Majesties</hi> late Indulgence, some of the Episcopal Perswasion have not yet abated of their Rigour; but continue still to urge <hi>Subscription</hi> and <hi>Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> alleageing in Excuse that their Oaths formerly taken do still oblige them; they have hereby given a very just occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to have the <hi>Covenant</hi> revived, and this Question seriously examined, whether that <hi>Oath</hi> doth not much more strictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leige the Takers; since the Matter of it, is (not like theirs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout pressing of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> i. e. of things which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves acknowledg to be <hi>Indifferent,</hi>) but, about things much more substantial; and likewise the manner of Expression, is so strict and Particular, that there is not the least roome left for any Evasion.</p>
            <p>In the manageing of this Enquiry, that what shall be said may find the better reception amongst Equall and unprejudiced Readers, it will be necessary for the Undertaker, to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from the suspicion of being a Party, least he should be thought to plead, not so much the Cause of Truth, as of his own Concernement. And therefore I do profess, 1. That I nev<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> took the <hi>Covenant.</hi> 2. That I ventured the loss of all my Fortunes, rather than I would <hi>Submit</hi> to the Authourity which Imposed it. 3. That I then did, and still doe conceive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119308:4"/>that the Arbitrary, and, as I think, Illegal Imposing of that Oath; and the undoing of so many thousands, meerly because they conscientiously declined it (amongst whom my own near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Relations were none of the least sufferers) this was a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, to say no more, much misbecoming Christians. For though to swear, in some Cases and with due Caution, may be Lawfull; yet sine an Oath, like other Acts of Religion, is to be Free and Voluntary; and of the two, rather to be Feared and Avoided, than rashly entred into; then to offer violence to the Conscience of any, and by Penalties of what kind soever, to force an Oath, cannot be justified by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates either of <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Reason;</hi> as being contrary to that Known Rule of Equal Justice, <hi>scil. of Doing, as we would be done by;</hi> and likewise to those other Precepts, whereby <hi>Tender Consciences,</hi> though in matters of less concernement, are expresly secured and provided for.</p>
            <p>But yet notwithstanding all this, I have so Just and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall a Regard for Truth; and withall so great a Fear of the sad and miserable Consequences of <hi>Perjury;</hi> that, in spite of my own Prejudices, I think the <hi>Covenant</hi> is still obligeing, if not to the whole Nation, yet at least, to all those particular persons, who entred into it: and that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Because, I never yet saw any Argument, which did clearly evince, that the <hi>matter</hi> of that <hi>Oath,</hi> was in it self <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Because the <hi>Manner</hi> of <hi>Imposing,</hi> though <hi>Illegall</hi> and <hi>Injust,</hi> yet cannot Null the <hi>Obligation</hi> of any <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For proof of the First Assertion, I will not insist upon the First, and the Four last Articles of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> wherein, <hi>Reformation of Religion, Defence of his Majesties Person and just Prerogative, Bringing of Delinquents to Punishment, Preserving of the Fundamentall Laws and Liberties of the Nation,</hi> and the like, are sworne to: for these carry their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119308:5"/>their own Equity and Reasonableness so apparent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that it would be but lost Labour to Defend them. As for that Clause of the third Article, at which many sober, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interested Persons have taken Exception; <hi>viz.</hi> the swearing to defend the Kings Person <hi>in Defence of Religion,</hi> which seems to lay a Restriction, as if the <hi>King</hi> were no longer to be defended, than might consist with the good of <hi>Religion;</hi> if this indeed was intended for the sense of it, I shall not scruple to say, that it is most <hi>Unchristian;</hi> for the Authority of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces depends not at all upon their <hi>Religion,</hi> but upon their <hi>Right</hi> to governe: and were our Princes now, as the Emperours formerly were, open and professed Infidels, yet could we not lawfully deny them our Obedience in all <hi>Civill</hi> things, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the Defence both of their <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> though to our own Temporall Injury; as the two great Apostles both <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> expresly affirme. But, without enquiring into the secret designe and meaning of the Contrivers (which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps might be bad enough) the words themselves — <hi>in the defence of Religion,</hi> are capable of this fair Interpretation —so farre as Religion doth oblige and warrant us; which, as I said before, our Religion doth universally and unlimitedly bind us, though not alwayes to act for, yet alwayes not to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist their power, nor to violate their Person.</p>
            <p>But to omit this, which seems to be meerly a Cavil, that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle which is opposed with greatest vigour and strength of Reason, is the second against <hi>Praelacy;</hi> whereby not only the <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> but likewise the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Bishops,</hi> seems to be decryed as <hi>Anti-christian;</hi> and here two things are usually insisted upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Episcopacy</hi> or the subordination between <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> is commonly presumed to be <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> and though Learned Men differ much in their judgment about it, yet none hath so clearly resolved the doubt, but that, 1. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119308:5"/>Distinction which our Saviour himself seems to put between the twelve Apostles, and his seaventy Disciples 2. The Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, and Preeminence, at least in point of Order, which the <hi>Apostles</hi> had over the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> whom they ordained. 3. The examples of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> who were delegated by the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> to Ordain <hi>Elders</hi> by their single Authority. 4. The Consent of Antiquity, which, as the best and most unsuspected Records testifie, do all avouch and own this Constitution. All these Instances do conclude thus much, that if <hi>Episcopacy</hi> be not perfectly, and at all points <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> yet at least it may be evinced to be more <hi>Apostolical,</hi> more Ancient, and more defensible both by Primitive Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise and Impartiall Reason, than any other Forme of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governement whatever. And therefore to cry it down, as the Covenant doth, for <hi>Antichristian,</hi> before they have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered the Reasons, which prove it to be <hi>Divine;</hi> this, say some, is a proceeding no wayes justifiable, as being both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable and absurd in it self, and likewise since that, found very Inconvenient; because many have Petitioned against Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters maintenance, and particularly <hi>Tithes,</hi> as <hi>Antichristian;</hi> which those, who have laboured to pull down <hi>Bishops</hi> under that Stile, though they are willing to reteine, yet can but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill, if at all defend; since upon enquiry they will be found, as to the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of them, to be founded only upon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rules of Analogy and Interpretative Reason from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but of much less Antiquity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A second Objection is, that <hi>Episcopacy</hi> with all the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances</hi> and <hi>Appendixes,</hi> covenanted against in that second Article, is confirmed by the Law of the Land, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the so much contended for <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for any to take them away is absolutely unlawfull. But upon this Objection I will not enlarge, because it may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119308:6"/> 1. That there is no Law meerly Humane, but, if it be found Inconvenient, the same Authority which made, may without Injury to any, abrogate it; and though all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of any place, are tied to preserve the Laws, that can be only meant of the Laws in Being, and never yet did hinder but that New Laws might daily be made, since the Supreme and Legislative Powers cannot be bound, but by the generall Rules of Equity and Convenience, of which they alone are Judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no part of the Popish Religion, as it is opposite to the Reformed, but was once established by our Laws; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulary the <hi>Popes Supremacy;</hi> which certainly none of those who are most zealous for <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> but will affirme that it was lawfully taken away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Law, which is to be the only Rule in things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Religion, is the Word of God; and therefore if the Supposition in the Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> as there expressed, is <hi>Antichristian,</hi> can be proved; it will be in vain to alleage in defence of it any Nationall Constitutions, which cannot be any longer Obligatory to any, than as they have a Consistency with that Divine and Heavenly Law.</p>
            <p>The first Objection therefore is of most weight, and by all persons concerned in taking the Covenant, ought to be most severely Enquired into, least they should be found <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by rash flying into the other extreame, to destroy what they should only have amended; and to pull up the Tree, which had they only pruned and pared away the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Branches, would have been of exceeding Use; like him in the Fable, who knew no other way to prevent drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness, but by cutting up the Vines.</p>
            <p>That I may (as a person unconcerned, and therefore likely to be clear either from Partiality or Designe) free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discover, where I thinke the stresse of the Cause lies,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119308:6"/>and how it is to be stated; I shall premise these three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Calling of Gospel-ministers,</hi> as distinct both in <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> from the People they Preach to, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side over, is <hi>Jure divino.</hi> And this I do not ground upon those Reasons, which are commonly alleaged: As, 1. A ministeriall succession in all Ages; which is hard to prove, and, because of our seccession from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> (which abounds in such kind of Arguments) is altogether Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Nor, 2. Because our Saviour did himself constantly Preach the Gospel, and appointed his Disciples to do the like; after whose Ascension, the Apostles, especially <hi>Paul,</hi> did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain <hi>Elders</hi> in all the Churches which they had planted, to be continually resident. For these are Instances which tell us only what was then done, not what alwayes should be done; nor can any thing of direct proof, but only by way of <hi>Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> be deduced from them: and the most that such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments amount to, is only to prove the <hi>Calling convenient</hi> or <hi>fitting,</hi> but not <hi>necessary.</hi> The Reasons therefore which I found the <hi>Jus divinum</hi> of a <hi>Gospel-Ministry</hi> upon, are; 1. Our Saviours great instance, and frequent urging of his Apostles to pray, that God <hi>would send labourers into his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest:</hi> i. e. not such as should Preach now and then, but such as should make it their business, as the word <hi>labourers</hi> plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies. And therefore the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> that there might not want a race of <hi>Ministers,</hi> commands his Son <hi>Timothy</hi> to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what he knew, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>faithfull, industrious men, who might be able to teach others;</hi> which charge, had he not intended that they should teach authoritatively, and by way of Office, would have been altogether impertinent. For what need there have been select men appointed for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, if every man were permitted to be a <hi>Teacher.</hi> 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God doth still impart variety of gifts; as <hi>Tongues, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119308:7"/>Prophesie, Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. though not in so plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull a measure, yet for the same end as formerly, <hi>viz. for the building up his Church, and the compleating of his mystical body.</hi> And therefore as the Apostle asks, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Are all Apostles? Are all Teachers? Have all the gift of edifying?</hi> He that hath, let him look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himself as called unto that duty for which he is gifted; and that to do it not desultorily and by the by, but by constant waiting upon his Ministry, as the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces directly commands. 3. Because of those inavoidable ill consequences which would follow in the Church of Christ, if there were no setled <hi>Ministry</hi> to attend in it. For as it is in a State, that which is left at randome, for any to do if they please, if it be a matter of difficulty and trouble, is usually neglected by all: So will it happen in the Assemblies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which the Apostle <hi>James</hi> warns us against, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>many teachers,</hi> and no learners, would only beget pride and contempt in the ignorant, and negligence and remisness in the knowing; and so for want of some able and fixed Pilot to sit at the Helm, and guide the Ship, it will inevitably miscarry. Therefore without undertaking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, how many persons shall belong to each <hi>Pastors</hi> charge; nor defining by whom the respective Preachers shall be chosen; this I affirm, that in every <hi>Church,</hi> i. e. <hi>Congregation</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> there is to be a Preaching-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, distinct and separate for that employment, and that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The second thing I premise is, That according to the Scripture, all Gospel-Ministers, <hi>qua tales,</hi> are equall; and no one hath in that respect, any Jurisdiction or Authority above another. This is plain from that of our Saviour, where forbidding his <hi>Disciples</hi> all <hi>supremacy</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> he gives this reason for it, <hi>For ye</hi> saith he, <hi>are brethren.</hi> And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119308:7"/>suitable to this intimation was the practice of the Apostles, for in that first generall, and last holy Synod, they would not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to determine any thing, without the consent and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15. Gal. 2.</note> Thus <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> who were in respect of gifts accounted <hi>chief</hi> among them, yet gave the <hi>right hand of fellowship,</hi> i. e. acknowledged an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in Office unto <hi>Paul,</hi> though he were an Apostle of a later edition, and less standing then themselves. So <hi>Paul</hi> doth in many places call <hi>Timothy, Agollos, Sosthenes,</hi> and others, his <hi>fellow-labourers</hi> and <hi>co-workers in the Ministry;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ep. c. 5.</note> and <hi>Peter</hi> in that very place where he forbids <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>to exercise Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship over their Past or all cares,</hi> that he might induce them to humility by his own example, he doth stile himself <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their <hi>fellow-Elder</hi> and Partner. Hence is it that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Names there are which seem to denote <hi>dignity</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Rulers, Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Teachers, Bishops</hi> or <hi>Overseers,</hi> and the like; all these throughout <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles, are given without distinction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> concerning whom he writes. And the reason of this Equality is manifest, because the proper business of a <hi>Minister</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> is to Preach the Gospel, and to convert souls: in the discharge of which work, though all have not the same skill and ability, yet all have the same <hi>Commission.</hi> Which doth not run <hi>Ite, Dominamini— Goe, bear Rule over,</hi> but <hi>Ite, Praedicate, goe, preach unto every Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third and last thing I will premise is this: That notwithstanding this, as I may call it, Fundamentall and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Equality, yet it is very Lawfull for a Company of <hi>Presbyters</hi> (the ancient stint was Forty, as appears out of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s test,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6.</note> cited by <hi>Eusebius</hi>) to Elect and Choose one out of their Number, that he may <hi>Preside</hi> in their Meetings, moderate in their Debates, and be vested
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119308:8"/>with some eminent Acts of Power, as Laying on of Hands in Ordination, Pronouncing of sentence against Offenders, and the like, which yet he is so to exercise as to acknowledge, that he hath no Paramount Authority of his own, but what he solely derives from the Consent of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> over which he Presides. And this is the true Platform of that Primitive Episcopacy, which, for the forementioned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, may lay a good claim to <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> as being best suited to Apostolicall Precept and ancient usage, which where it may be had pure and incorrupt, is the best Interpreter of Controverted and ambiguous Texts.</p>
            <p>These things being premised, to apply what I have said, particularly to the Covenant, I affirm</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if the Covenant be construed to exclude the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of <hi>Bishops,</hi> and that <hi>Superiority</hi> which by mutuall consent may be placed in the <hi>Presbyteries</hi> over each other; then is it utterly unlawfull, because it unduely deprives <hi>Christians</hi> of the Liberty to erect a Government in the Church, which the Word of God doth insinuate, Antiquity defends, and Reason may demonstrate to be absolutely the best. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. If that Article barely means, as the words seem to sound, the pulling down of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> i. e. <hi>Episcopacy</hi> with those Appendixes, so chosen, and so governing, as is there expressed: then is it so far from being unlawfull, that I have often wondered the <hi>Bishops</hi> did not of themselves alter what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was grievous and offensive to the people, rather then they would let the Nation enter into a Covenant and Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation against them, and expose their <hi>Order</hi> it self to censure. For all the while they continue their ancient frame and Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, they will hardly excuse themselves from being (I was about to say, as some angry men do, <hi>Antichristian,</hi> but to use a milder expression) directly contrary to what the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119308:8"/>Bishops</hi> were, and to what an <hi>Apostolicall Bishop</hi> should be: And that in these three particulars;</p>
            <p n="1">1. In point of Choice and Designat on to that <hi>Office:</hi> which the <hi>Bishops</hi> now derive, not from the consent of those over whom they <hi>Preside,</hi> as was the Primitive usage, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the Supream Civill Magistrate; and so in strict propriety of Phrase, are rather the <hi>Kings Lords,</hi> then the <hi>Churches Bishops;</hi> whereby the Foundation of their <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> is shrewdly shaken; since it is evident, that the same Civil Power which creates, may dissolve them again, without the least violence offered, either to Scripture, or to Antiquity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In point of Power and Jurisdiction; which in <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> things, and over their Fellow-Ministers (I mean any farther then by consent, is directly for bidden all <hi>Scriptu e-Bishops,</hi> in those words of our Saviour; where speaking of the Impotent Rule of Heathen Princes, who thinke of no other <hi>Paradise,</hi> but <hi>Earthly Power,</hi> he concludes with this, prohibition to his Disciples— <hi>It shall not be so, among you; but he that is the greatest among you, let him be servant of all.</hi> In obedience to which command, the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> doth expressely disclaime <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; i. to <hi>Lord it over the Faith</hi> or <hi>Conscientious Perswasion</hi> of any; how small or Indifferent soever the thing was which he scrupled at; and of himselfe he professeth, that he would not so much as <hi>Eat Flesh all his dayes, rather then his Brother should be offended;</hi> How much lesse, thinke we, would that blessed Apostle have enjoyned any thing lesse materiall upon the Practise of any; in which particular, I am sorry to read, that the <hi>Bishops</hi> heretofore did exercise a power very different from that which the commands of our Saviour, and the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his. Apostles doe warrant, who, certainly ought to be the only Gospell-Patternes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119308:9"/> 3. Lastly, in point of Revenew and Maintenance; which Consists principally in <hi>Impropriate Tithes.</hi> For if it be a question not yet determined amongst Divines, whether <hi>Tithes be due to Gospell Ministers Jure Divino;</hi> then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for them to be alienated from the <hi>Preaching Ministers</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom, by the Apostles Canon, a double Honour, both of <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Revenew</hi> is due) and given to the support of those, to speake modestly, preach not over-often: This may be stiled, a worse and more unjustifiable <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> than that which is now complained of.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore that since the <hi>Covenant</hi> may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood only, 1. Of paring away the Impertinent and Uselesse parts of <hi>Episcopacy;</hi> and, 2. Of taking away not the <hi>Order,</hi> but the <hi>Undue Dominion</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops;</hi> for where they were not <hi>chosen</hi> they can have no <hi>Right,</hi> and where they have no <hi>Right,</hi> they ought to have no <hi>Power:</hi> hence it followes, that that Article of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is Materially Lawfully; and by the meere equity of it, doth oblige all Christians, to endeavour a <hi>Reformation,</hi> although they never had; but much more those, who already have entered into an Oath for that purpose. And so much for the First assertion.</p>
            <p>The second Assertion was this, That the <hi>Manner of Imposeing, though absolutly unlawsull, yet cannot null the Obligation of any Oath, after it is taken.</hi> And the Reason of this is cleare, because the force of an Oath depends not upon the Inducement which made us take it, (for then when the Occasion which made us sweare, once ceases, the Obligation of every Oath would cease likewise, which is Absurd) but upon the Reverence we owe to God, by whose Name we sweare, which being once interposed, the Oath is ratified in Heaven, and alwayes obliges either to <hi>Performance,</hi> or else to <hi>Divine Punishment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119308:9"/>
            <p> And because this Reason, though cleare and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strative, may seeme too close and Compact; for Reason, like cloth of Tissue, is best seene when it is most displayd; therefore I have enlarged my selfe upon it in the following Question; which though breifly (for neither the Age nor my own Temper can endure great Books) yet is I hope, suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently stated, to the satisfaction of all sober men: At least I have in it discharged my own Conscience, which was to doe my part, as a <hi>Minister</hi> of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> in endeavouring to obviate and hinder the sin of the Times, and that is, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardlesseness of Oathes;</hi> For which, it is to be feared, that God may still have a Controversie with this Land; and send <hi>a sword amongst us to avenge the Quarrell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L vit. 26.</note> not of ours any longer, but according to the Scripture-stile, <hi>of his Covenant;</hi> as being Solemnely taken, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>only engaged in. And however it may please God to wave his usuall method of Providence, in proceeding to be a <hi>Swift witnesse against the False Swearer;</hi> yet,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note> at the last day, when <hi>Idle words</hi> shall be accounted for, no Empty Subterfuges, nor poore Politicall Pleas will serve the turne; but the <hi>Covenant-breakers</hi> will then be left as Defencelesse and as Naked of excuse, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, when he had nothing but Fig-leaves to cover him. From which Irrecoverable, and none knows how suddaine, mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we are bound to pray and indeavor, that all our <hi>Fellow Christians, our Brethren after the Flesh,</hi> may be delivered; and to conjure them by all the sacred ties of Love to us, or to their own soules; that they will not allow themselves to violate their Engagement; or to doe more in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, then what they have just ground from the <hi>word of God</hi> to believe, that God hereafter will acquit them for. To which Pious and Christian designes, if this short discourse may at all contribute, it hath attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119308:10"/>that end, for which it was mainly written, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>A Treatise concerning Oathes; and particularly the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaton of a forced Oath.</head>
            <p>NOt to trouble the Reader or my self with a tedious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, I shall briefly explain, whatever I find from Scripture that concerns the Nature or Obligation of an Oath; and herein I will enquire into these three things;
<list>
                  <item>1. What is an <hi>Oath.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Whether it be <hi>Lawfull to take an Oath.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Whether <hi>a forced Oath, after it is once taken can lawfully be broken,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In Answer to the first Quere, I find to Scripture that this is the most proper definition of an <hi>Oath,</hi> viz. An Oath is <hi>a solemn Invocation of God to be a witness to the truth of what we speak, and likewise an Imprecation of Divine vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our selves in case we be found to speak falsely.</hi> In which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition there are these two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Oath is a <hi>solemn Invocation of God to be a witness to the truth of what we speak.</hi> I call it a <hi>solemn Invocation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the most usuall posture wherein Oathes were made, was by <hi>hands lift up on High.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note> Hence <hi>Abraham</hi> mentioning the Oath he had made, sayes, <hi>I have lift up my hand to the most high God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12. Rev. 16.</note> Thus the Angel in <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Apocalypse</hi> is brought in with these words, that <hi>he lifted up his hand to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and sware by him that liveth for ever.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 32.</note> Nay God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> speaketh in the same manner, <hi>I lift up my hand to Heaven, and I say, I live for ever;</hi> which is all one with this in another place,<note place="margin">Isa 49.</note>
               <hi>I sweare by my self.</hi> Now this posture of <hi>lifting up the hand,</hi> is a posture of Prayer; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119308:10"/>to that of the Apostle, <hi>I will that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim 2.</note> For as when we Petition God, we ought to use reverent gesture; so much more when we appeal to him; and therefore those gestures of body in swearing, which do not denote inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and awe of mind, are too light and triviall for so weighty and sacred an action. 2. It is a solemn Invocation <hi>of God to be a witness;</hi> and this will appear by those formes of Oathes, which we find recorded in Scripture, wherein the Name of God, or else some Attribute of his is expresly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; as in that <hi>Oath</hi> which <hi>Abraham</hi> exacted from his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.</note>
               <hi>I will,</hi> saith he, <hi>make thee swear by the Lord, the God of Heaven, and the God of the Earth.</hi> So in the Covenant or League between <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note>
               <hi>Laban</hi> sware by the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Nahor;</hi> but <hi>Jacob</hi> sware <hi>by the fear of his Father Isaac;</hi> i. e. by that God which his Father <hi>Isaac</hi> feared.<note place="margin">Gen. 42.</note> Hence is that command twice repeated in the Law, that <hi>they should fear the Lord, and swear by his Name;</hi> therefore all Oaths by the Creatures, such as was <hi>Josephs, by the life of Pharaoh;</hi> and the <hi>Pharisees, by their Head, by the Temple, by the Altar,</hi> and the like, were unlawfull,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> since they did put the Creature into the place of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are expresly forbidden by our Saviour; although even such Oaths do oblige, as our Saviour argues, since <hi>he that swears by the Temple, swears by it; and by him that dwells there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in:</hi> i. e. He that swears by the Creature, swears by that, and likewise by the God of the Creature; and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect obliges himself.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Oath is <hi>an Imprecation of divine vengeance upon our selves, in case we be found to swear falsly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And this is imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the very name, which in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> signifies both an <hi>Oath</hi> and a <hi>Curse;</hi> because a <hi>Curse</hi> is alwayes annexed as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of an <hi>Oath.</hi> And in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 29.</note> where <hi>Moses</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119308:11"/>the Law of God, he tells them, that <hi>they should enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant with the Lord, and into his Oath,</hi> which he calls presently, <hi>the words of this Curse;</hi> and again, <hi>the Curses of this Covenant;</hi> because of that fatall and inseparable connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is between an <hi>Oath broken,</hi> and a <hi>Curse,</hi> deserved at least to attend it. The same is likewise implyed in what is said, that an <hi>Oath</hi> was an Invocation of God <hi>to be a witness;</hi> which in the <hi>Hebrew dialect,</hi> doth not only signifie to <hi>Hear,</hi> but likewise to <hi>Punish;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> as <hi>Laban</hi> to <hi>Jacob, See,</hi> saith he, <hi>man is by, God is witness betwixt me and thee:</hi> that is, as he himself interprets it, <hi>the Lord judge betwixt us.</hi> Whence it is that God threatens by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.</note> to be <hi>a swift witness against the false Swearer:</hi> i. e. speedily, and without delay, to avenge himself of him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The second thing to be enquired into, is, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lawfull to take an Oath?</hi> This I know is commonly presumed, and the contrary opinion is loaded with so much scorn and obloquy, that it may seem needless to discourse about it. But that I may give all men, how erroneous soever, their due, I think those who hold it utterly unlawfull to swear, and in pursuance of that Tenet, suffer with so much constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, are rather to be pitied, nay commended, for their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness; then either to be bitterly censured, or have any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered to their consciences: especially since they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not barely upon an obstinate humour, but upon this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Reason and Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because our Saviour and his Apostle <hi>James,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. Jac. 5.</note> doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in direct terms, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and, <hi>Above all things swear not.</hi> Which words, if they be taken universally, as prohibiting all manner of Oaths, I do not see but the <hi>Texts</hi> may well warrant such an Exposition; at least they cannot be thought unworthy of the name or usage of Christians, who are willing to observe our Saviours precepts in their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119308:11"/>and most comprehensive Latitude.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because in the Time of the Law, when Swearing was allowed, yet it was looked upon as a signe of a good man to <hi>Feare an Oath;</hi> i. e. To feare to take one; as the opposition in <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 2. sheweth, where among wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ungodly men, is ranked— <hi>he that Sweareth;</hi> to whom is opposed by way of contradistinction, <hi>he that feares an Oath</hi> i. e. That doth not sweare at all; as the words may very well be interpreted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Because, to sweare is a thing, at the best, permitted only, it is no where commanded. For those words in the Commandement,<note place="margin">Ex. 20.</note>
               <hi>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine,</hi> is according to our Saviours interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a command only, that <hi>we should not break our Oath,</hi> but not that we should take one. Like that concerning marriage, of which the Apostle saith,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> that <hi>a woman is bound by the Law</hi> (not to marry, for that she may forbeare if she please, but) <hi>to be true to her Husband so long as she is married.</hi> So the Precept in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c.12.</note>
               <hi>Thou shalt serve the Lord, and swear by his name,</hi> is no Positive Command that we should sweare at all, but only a direction in what manner and by whose name we should sweare, when we have just occasion to do it. I can remember but two cases in Scripture, wherein an <hi>Oath</hi> is peremptorily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: the one is the case of a thing, which was borrowed and lost no <hi>witnesse being by;</hi> then he who borrowed it,<note place="margin">Ex. 22.</note> was obliged to cleare himselfe by an Oath; and that, not to the Party in private, but before the Magistrate; as those words clearly imply; <hi>There shall be an Oath between them</hi> i. Administred by such as have Authority to judg and decide Controversies. Another case wherein an Oath was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, was that of a woman,<note place="margin">Numb. 5.</note> who being by her Husband suspected of Adultery, and yet wanted proofe to cleare the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119308:12"/>matter of Fact, she was to be brought unto the High Priest; who, together with giving her the <hi>Bitter water,</hi> was to <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure her by an Oath,</hi> to which she was obliged to say <hi>Amen;</hi> and to take the curse upon her selfe, in case she had been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But both these were extraordinary cases, and such as could not be decided by witnesses, as both the places mentioned doe expresly testifie; but in every thing else which related to Judiciall proceedings, the matters were to be ended by <hi>Witnesses</hi> without swearing, as is plaine in the command; which doth not run, thou shalt not sweare Falsly, but, <hi>Thou shalt not bear False witnesse against thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Because the custome of exacting an Oath,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> proceeds <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>From evill,</hi> if not otherwise, yet thus farre, in that it intimates, he who does it, suspects his Neighbours Truth and Veracity; which however Heathens have just reason to doe, yet Christians are utterly forbidden: for it is their duty,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 1 Cor. 13.</note>
               <hi>To speake the truth in Love one to another;</hi> and the Apostle stated it, <hi>That Love thinketh no evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Lastly, because that Inconvenience, which, amongst many, makes swearing in a Court of Justice to be held so necessary, <hi>viz.</hi> Because many may be thought to value an Oath, who would not otherwise regard their single Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; This indeed is neither True nor Inconvenient: not True, since daily experience tells us, that men are Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as apt to sweare a Lye as to speake it: there being no Imaginable Reason why he who breakes Gods command in one thing, should observe it in another: which is apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seene in such who in common Discourse, sweare frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their very Oathes doe for the most part make them to be discredited: according to what God speakes of his own People, though they <hi>swear the Lord liveth; yet they swear falsly.</hi> 2. Not Inconvenient, because it is easie to make
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119308:12"/>that provision, which the Law of God did, that the <hi>False Witnesse</hi> should have the very same punishment inflicted on him whether for Life or Estate,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.16.20.</note> which he had designed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Innocent Neighbour; which if it were once imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally executed the custome of swearing would cease, with the pretended Necessity of it</p>
            <p>Besides these Arguments which may be enforced against swearing in generall; there are Two more of great weight against Promissory Oaths in particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because an <hi>Oath</hi> is a <hi>Bond</hi> or <hi>Ty;</hi> so we find it called <hi>Num.</hi> 30. <hi>If a man sweare, to bind his soul with a Bond.</hi> And so all along that Chapter. For as <hi>cords</hi> and <hi>chaines</hi> doe bind the Body, so doe <hi>Oaths,</hi> the soule: and as farre as we have sworne, so much of our Liberty we have parted with; which both as men, we ought to value; and as Christians we are bound to preserve: because a Free use of Indifferent things, is part of our Saviours purchase. And therefore, by the way, those Voluntary and Unnecessary Vowes of <hi>Perpetuall Chastity, Pilgrimage, Fasting, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and</hi> the like; are so farre from being <hi>Meritorious,</hi> that they are most highly displeasing to God, as being made without, nay against, his warrant: And will at the last day, instead of Reward, meet only with a <hi>Quis requisivit</hi>— <hi>Who hath required these things at your hands?</hi> who bid you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest your selves of that Liberty, which Christ at so deare a rate purchased for you? And, when there are so many things that lye undone by you, who bad you load your selves with the Unprofitable Burden of uncommanded du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because of the Uncertainty of future things.<note place="margin">Eccl. 11.2.</note> What the wise man speakes concerning Liberality to the Poore, <hi>Give a Portion to seven, and also to eight, for thou dost not know what evill shall be upon the Earth</hi>— may be inverted, as to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119308:13"/>this businesse of swearing, <hi>Forbeare to do it, for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not what evill may be upon the Earth.</hi> The world, as it was made a Round Globe, so its Morall or Politicall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, like its Naturall, always in a Circle. Life it selfe is called by the Apostle <hi>James <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i.</hi> not the <hi>Course</hi> as we render it,<note place="margin">c. 3.6.</note> but, the <hi>Wheele of our Nativity.</hi> Upon which consideration, he sharply reprehends those, who take upon them so much as peremptorily to promise,<note place="margin">c. 4.</note> that they will <hi>Buy</hi> and <hi>sell; whereas,</hi> saies he, <hi>ye know not what shall be to morrow.</hi> But if the uncertainiy of Future things ought to keepe us from bare promising, much more ought it to make us cautious in Swearing, for the same Reason, which the Apostle there gives, because we doe not know what shall be to morrow. And therefore for any to swear Absolutely, <hi>I will doe such, or such a thing;</hi> and not leave himselfe that Retreat, which by the same Apostle is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, <hi>If the Lord will, we shall live and doe this or that;</hi> this would be nothing else, but on the one hand to Tempt God, and to confine the Free and Arbitrary Actings of his Omnipotence; and on the other hand, to destroy our selves, by running upon the Rocks either of <hi>Perjury,</hi> if we breake, or else of <hi>Poverty,</hi> if we keepe our Oathes: and when it once comes to that <hi>Dilemma,</hi> few there are of so <hi>Tender consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> but will streine at a Distinction; which had they at first directly denied to sweare, they would not be liable to the temptation of.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding what I have said, I cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that it is utterly unlawfull to sweare, either by way of Assertion. <hi>i. e.</hi> when we assert the truth of a thing, to which we our selves are privy, and therefore cannot, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we will, be mistaken: by way of Promise, provided that the thing we sweare, be in it selfe Lawfull, and in our Power to doe it. And my Reasons are</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119308:13"/> 1. Because I find the Patriarches, before the giving the Law, did it, as without scruple on their owne parts, so without check on Gods. Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Isaac</hi> made a League with <hi>Abimelech: Jacob</hi> with <hi>Laban;</hi> and in private <hi>Abraham</hi> exacted an Oath, from his servant; <hi>Jacob</hi> from his brother <hi>Esau,</hi> and afterwards from his son <hi>Joseph;</hi> which last Action is so mentioned by the Apostle,<note place="margin">H. b. 11.</note> as withall it is commended as an Effect of his <hi>Faith.</hi> Now, though I will grant that examples prove nothing against a Rule, yet when a Rule is in controversy, the Constant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of Holy men ought to guide us in our Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because when <hi>Jacob</hi> in his flight prayed to God for his Protection, he at the same time made a <hi>vow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.22.</note> that he would erect an Oratory at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and for the maintenance of Gods Publicke worship, devote <hi>the Tenth</hi> of his Estate; which Action of his, is so farre from being censured, that God mentions it with speciall Approbation;<note place="margin">Gen. 31.13. Ps. 15.4.</note>
               <hi>I am,</hi> saith he, <hi>the God of Bethel, where thou anointedst the Pillar, and where thou vowedst a vow unto me.</hi> And when <hi>David</hi> reckons up the Characters of a man who was fit to be an Inhabitant of <hi>Sion,</hi> he makes this one, not that he never swore, but that he never forswore himselfe: <hi>He is one,</hi> saith he, who <hi>sweares to his Hurt, and changeth not.</hi> Which implies that to sweare was Lawfull. And therefore <hi>David</hi> in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession to God useth this expression, as a signe of his sincere and unfeigned Piety— <hi>I have sworne and I will performe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 119.</note>
               <hi>that I will keepe thy Righteous judgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> doth expresse it as the Happy Condition of Gospell-times, that they should sweare,<note place="margin">Jer. 5.2.</note>
               <hi>the Lord liveth, in Truth, in Righteousnesse, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> i. Not that they should utterly absteine from Oathes, but use them with due Care and Circumspecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119308:14"/>fully understanding what and why the sweare.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Saviours, and likewise the Apostle <hi>James</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, of <hi>swear not at all.</hi> Need not to be understood universally, no more then when we are commanded to say <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> that we are thereby tied to use those Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Phrases; but may very well be limited to Private Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, as the words following intimate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, — <hi>Let your Communication, be altogether free from swearing,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as it is a sacred, so it ought to be a solemne Action. For were our Saviours words to be literally taken, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be imagined that the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> should in so many places, use expressiones, that if they are not, yet they are little lesse then Oaths,— as <hi>By your Rejoycing,</hi> in <hi>the Presence of God I lye not:</hi> with many the like; and above all,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.21.</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I Invoke God as a witnesse upon my soule;</hi> which words containe the very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of an Oath, since therein he Invokes God <hi>as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> i. as a Judge to punish him if he sweares falsly: for the Hebrew Notation of the word <hi>to witnesse,</hi> signifies <hi>to Judge,</hi> as I have formerly observed.</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore that before a Magistrate, in a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>case, and upon a just call; it is not Unlawfull to take an Oath: though I must confesse, the former Arguments weigh so much with me, that I thinke, if lawfully we may, it is much more Pious and Adviseable in Christian Prudence to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide the Occasion of swearing, then voluntarily to run into it. As the Apostle speakes concerning <hi>Marrying,</hi> which is an Action very lawfull too;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> so say I concerning <hi>swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; He that sweares</hi> (upon those Cautions and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations that I have premised) <hi>doth well,</hi> but he that sweares not, doth better. And so much for the second Question.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Question is—whether a <hi>Forced Oath, after
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119308:14"/>it is taken, may Lawfully be broken.</hi> For the right stating of which I premise these two things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That the Question must be understood of a thing in it selfe not Unlawfull; for no man can be obliged, whether willingly or unwillingly, to commit a sin.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That though to speake properly no Oath can be <hi>Forced,</hi> because no man can be brought into such a streight, but he may refuse to sweare or to do any other Action, which he thinkes unlawfull, if he will, yet in compliance with Custome, that Oath, which a man takes upon some Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of violence, that is intended to him, if he should refuse to sweare, I call Involuntary or Forced— and this I say doth as much oblige, as if no Force did at all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene; which I shall prove, first by Instances secondly by Reason.</p>
            <p n="1">1. My first Instance shall be that of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> who was <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> prisoner, and had taken an Oath of Fealty and Alleageance to him, which, for the matter of it, was as unlawfull; as for the manner, Involuntary; for the condition of that Oath was to enslave both himselfe, and the children of <hi>Israel</hi> unto the arbitrary commands of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> as God himselfe expresses it, <hi>That the Kingdom might be base,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 17.14.</note>
               <hi>that it might not lift it selfe up; but that by keeping of his Covenant it might stand.</hi> This Oath <hi>Zedekiah</hi> (pretending no doubt, that it was Unlawfull, that it was against the fundamentall Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Judea,</hi> and that he himselfe was <hi>under a Force</hi> at the time of taking it, with the like Thin and Airy excuses) present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after breakes, and all <hi>Israel</hi> with him: <hi>But,</hi> saith God, shall he prosper? <hi>shall he escape, that doth such things? or shall be breake the Govenant and be delivered? seeing he despised the Oath by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant, when loe he had given his hand;</hi> (i. by hands lifted up, had solemnly ratified it) <hi>As I live, saith the Lord,</hi> surely, <hi>Mine Oath that he hath broken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.12, 13</note>
               <hi>and my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that he hath despised, even it will I recompence upon his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119308:15"/>own Head.</hi> And we find that the event did answer this sad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, for in the <hi>Chronicles</hi> this is related as the Cause <hi>Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abs</hi> destruction, because <hi>he hearkened not to the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Jeremy,</hi> (who as we find in his Prophecies, did very often, and by reiterated Arguments, perswade him to continue his. Allegiance unto <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>) <hi>and brake his Oath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by the Lord; wherefore the wrath of the Lord arose against the People, untill there was no remedy.</hi> Wherein is insinuated, that that sin of Perjury is of so deep a die, and so provoking a nature, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can expiate it: I do not mean as to its guilt, (for that upon true Repentance may be done away by the Blood of Christ) but as to its Obligation unto temporall punishment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My second Instance shall be that of Souldiers taken in Battell, who swear to be true Prisoners; this Oath, all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether Christian or Heathen, do hold to be Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; and amongst others, <hi>Tully</hi> an Heathen Author, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates how infamous such persons were reputed among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who used indirect and subtle Acts to elude the force of that Oath; whereupon he layes down this Conclusion— <hi>Quicquid affirmatè, tanquam Deo teste juraveris, idtenendum est. Whatever you promise by an Oath, invoking God as a witness, that is to be held inviolable.</hi> Which pious speech, from the mouth of one, who had nothing but the Light of Nature to guide him, will certainly rise up in judgement against too many <hi>Christians,</hi> whom their <hi>Religion</hi> doth not carry so far, as meer <hi>Morality</hi> did him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Instance shall be the Oath made to a Thief up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the High-way, not to discover him: which the best Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suists have resolved to be Obligatory; and amongst other our Reverend and Learned Dr <hi>Sanderson,</hi> to whose unanswe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Reasons, I shall refer the Reader.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lastly, My last Instance shall be from such Oaths which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119308:15"/>are recorded in Scripture as Obligatory; and yet have much more to be said against them, to render them invalid and null, then Oaths merely forced; and these are of two sorts: 1. Rash and unadvised Oaths: 2. Oaths gained from us by deceit and fraud. Now if it shall appear that these Oaths do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige, then the Inference will be very good, that forced Oaths, where we know what we do, and have nothing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of but the violence intended us, do oblige us much more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Rash and unadvised Oaths are Obligatory. We are indeed commanded not to be <hi>Rash with our mouth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5.1.</note> but if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that Precaution, we will be <hi>Rash,</hi> it is but equall that we should smart for our Folly, and not adde un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Rashness</hi> in making an Oath, <hi>Presumption</hi> in breaking it. The Command is very peremptory,<note place="margin">Num. 30.2.</note>
               <hi>If a man vow a vow unto the Lord, or swear an Oath to binde his soul with a Bond; he shall not break his word; he shall do according to all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded out of his mouth.</hi> And lest any should pretend that they were not obliged, because they swore rashly and unadvisely; therefore it is repeated in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 23.21, 23.</note> with an express An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to that Objection. <hi>When thou shalt vow a vow unto the Lord, slack not to pay it; for the Lord thy God will surely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of thee. But if thou shalt forbear to vow, it shall be no sin unto thee.</hi> As if he had said; have a care what you do in this business of <hi>Oaths:</hi> do not meddle with them unawares, for if once you have bound your souls with these <hi>Bonds,</hi> God is then concerned to exact payment, and he will be sure to do it, because he had commanded you beforehand to be wary. And that this was the opinion and practice of the ancient, and as yet unsophisticated world, as well as the Command of God, will appear from two remarkable examples.<note place="margin">Judg. 11.30.</note> The one is of <hi>Jephtha,</hi> who vowed rashly enough, that in case God brought him home with victory, whatever came first out of his doors, he would offer it to the Lord; and when his Daughter to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119308:16"/>testifie her joy, was the first that met him at his return, he did not cast about for a distinction, but presently reflecting upon his Oath, <hi>Alas,</hi> saith he, <hi>my daughter, thou hast brought me very low; for I have opened my mouth unto the Lord, and I cannot go back.</hi> And she it seems was bred up in the same conscientious observance and <hi>fear of an Oath,</hi> for she encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges her Father; <hi>If,</hi> saith she, <hi>thou hast opened thy mouth unto the Lord,</hi> then do not dispute the point any further, but <hi>do unto me according to all that hath proceeded out of thy mouth.</hi> I do not think that <hi>Jephtha</hi> did proceed to sacrifice his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (as yet <hi>Josephus</hi> and many others do suppose) both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was a morall evil (and he that was so Religious and Circumspect in the observance of his vow, could not but know that no Oath did oblige him to commit of sin) but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise because his Daughter did desire him, that she might have leave <hi>to go</hi> only, and <hi>to bewail her virginity;</hi> intimating that the effect of her Fathers vow, was to dedicate her unto the service of God, as a <hi>Vestall Virgin.</hi> Yet the case was very sad, for it cut off from <hi>Jephtha</hi> all hopes of Issue, <hi>she being his only Childe.</hi> However the good man was so conscientious, that though his Oath was <hi>Rash,</hi> and the keeping of it was so fatall and destructive both to him and his Family; yet he durst not think of breaking it, because as he alleadged, <hi>he had open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his mouth unto the Lord, and therefore he could not go back.</hi> Another example is that of the <hi>Israclites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg 21.7.</note> who in the heat and fury of their Civil Warres, had <hi>sworn by the Lord, not to give of their Daughters unto the Benjamites for Wives:</hi> And perceiving at last their great Error, for by this means a whole Tribe was like to be utterly destroyed, we do not find, that upon pretence their Oath was <hi>Rash,</hi> they did presume to break it, but they rather advise their Brethren of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> to snatch Wives for themselves as they could get them, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the discontents of the injured Parents with this, <hi>Ye did
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119308:16"/>not give unto them,</hi> i. e. your Daughters for Wives, <hi>that you should be guilty,</hi> &amp;c. of breach of Oath. Perhaps some may object that both <hi>Jephtha</hi> and the <hi>Israelites</hi> were too nice and scrupulous; that they should only have repented of their sin in swearing, and all had been well; but let such well consider with themselves, what is the importance of that Command— <hi>When thou vowest a vow unto the Lord, deferre not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools</hi>—i. in men that say and unsay, that play as it were fast and loose with him. <hi>Pay that which thou hast vowed.</hi> And in case any should plead in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, I did it rashly; that is wholly taken away in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words, <hi>Say not thou before the Angel</hi>— (i. when he comes to require the payment of thy vow) <hi>it was an Errour,</hi> (i. I was mistaken, I did not consider of it, I knew not what I did, and the like) <hi>for why should God be angry at thy voice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the work of thy hands?</hi> i. God will not take such an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse to be valid, but will certainly punish thee for breaking thy Oath, though thou dost pretend it was unadvisedly taken.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Oathes gained from us by Fraud and Deccit, <hi>i.</hi> Such Oathes, into which we are meerly betrayed and cozened, and which, had we been rightly inform'd of all Circumstances, we would never have taken, doe notwithstanding oblige us. This was the Case so well known,<note place="margin">Josh. 9.</note> between <hi>Joshua</hi> and the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> they came to him under a False Name, for they said they were strangers, whereas they lived in the Countrey: they told him a False story, that they had been so many dayes on that Journey, as had worn out their Cloathes, and moulded their Provision. They came about an undue, and for ought I can see; an Unlawfull Errand, for it was to make a League with the <hi>Israelites;</hi> which, in many places, was expresly forbidden. Adde to this,<note place="margin">Deut 7.3. &amp;c.</note> that what <hi>Joshua</hi> and the Princes did, as it was without asking counsell
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119308:17"/>of the Lord, so it was utterly against the mind of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: for we find that they murmured against <hi>Joshua,</hi> and the Princes about it. Put all these Circumstances to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and one would thinke, if any thing could justify the breach of a <hi>Solemne League and Covenant, Joshuah</hi> had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for him. But we find that he durst not doe it, and that for but one unanswerable Argument, <hi>We have,</hi> saith he, <hi>sworn to them by the Lord, therefore we may not touch them.</hi> As if he had said, These men indeed deserve no favour at our hands, but we have used the name of our God to give them security by, therefore we may not touch them; for God will own and avenge their Quarrell: <hi>Therefore,</hi> saith he, <hi>we will let them live, lest wrath be upon us, because of the Oath that we sware unto them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 10.</note> Which conclusion of <hi>Joshua</hi>'s, as it was most pious in it self, so was it most pleasing to God; as he declared first by the miraculous victory he gave them, when they went to succour the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> as their Allyes and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates;</hi> and afterwards by the Plague; which he sent upon all <hi>Israel</hi> about four hundred and fifty years after, for the furious and bloody zeal of <hi>Saul,</hi> who did violate this League. From whence I draw this Inference, That if <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> Oath, which was directly forced; if the Oath of a Prisoner; and of a Traveller made to a Thief; if rash unadvised Oaths, and such into which we are meerly betrayed and cozened, do all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us; then it follows, that a precedent Force doth not at all melt the Obligation of a subsequent Oath. Which was my first Argument.</p>
            <p>My second Argument is from Reason; and that</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the nature of an Oath, which is an immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between God and the soul; and therefore the tye of it depends upon nothing else, but upon the Force and significan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the words wherein, and upon the Majesty of God by whom it is taken. Which is plain from that of <hi>Joshua,</hi> who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119308:17"/>alleadges no other Reason why he kept his League with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> but only this—<hi>We have sworn to them by the Lord, therefore we may not touch them.</hi> And when <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> sins are recapitulated, this is added by way of aggravation, that he broke his Oath unto <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by the Lord;</hi> the interposing of whose Name, gives eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Oath its sanction, and ought to make it sacred.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because of that great dishonour which is done to God, by the wilfull and deliberate breach of a solemn Oath. For since our honouring of God doth not consist in the deportment and carriage of our bodies before him, (for in this Hypocrisie may outact the most resolved Piety) but in that inward awe and veneration of mind which we have for so great a Majesty; there to trifle with Oaths, to pretend we were forced, or the like, when we swore by the Lord; and in that were credited, this is nothing else but to proclaim to the world, that we have low and mean thoughts of God, as if either he did not hear, or that he would not punish: which is nothing else but to question either his Providence, or his Justice, which are two Attributes of God, so essentiall to his Nature, and so necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be believed in the world, that God neither will nor can in honour suffer them to be questioned. And therefore to that Command against Forswearing, is added by way of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, that <hi>he will not hold them guiltless;</hi> i. he will assuredly punish <hi>such as take his Name in vain.</hi> And I think, if we search into former Ages and enquire, we shall not find many that did mock God (and certainly then we mock him, when we break an Oath which it is in our power to keep, because of some Inconvenience, which may thence arise unto our selves) and prosper.</p>
            <p>Lastly, The last Reason shall be from the Inconveniencies which will follow, if there be allowed the least Dispensation for Oaths. For in case a preceding Force shall be admitted as a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119308:18"/>sufficient defeazance for that Bond; then it follows—1. That all Warres must be prosecuted, not only to victory, but <hi>ad Internecionem,</hi> to the totall extirpation of the opposite Party; because there can be no tye upon them so strong, as may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to believe that ever they will surcease their Hostility. For if their <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Covenants</hi> be objected to them (as the <hi>Grecians</hi> in <hi>Homer <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Where are your Oaths, and right hands, to which we trusted?</hi>) they will presently reply, that they were compelled to swear, and therefore (according to this Divinity) absolved from their Oath, as soon as ever they took it. 2. There can be no possibility of any Agreement between Princes, especially where the one hath been conquered; for it will be easie (as it is too ordinary) for him to plead, that he was <hi>Forced</hi> unto Conditions of Peace. Lastly, if we grant this once, then immediately all <hi>Subjects</hi> will rise up in Arms against their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective <hi>Soveraigns.</hi> For it is evident, that were there not some kind of awe and constraint upon People, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter terms of Fealty and Allegiance. So that in all these cases, if an Oath because imposed by Force, doth not oblige, then are the foundations of all Society shaken, and the world will shortly be left a place of more dismall and Atheisticall Confusion, than Hell it self. For there <hi>the Devils believe there is a God, and tremble;</hi> but here the Name of God shall meerly be made a stale to deceive and undo others by.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, for I do not love to insist long up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so plain a Case; as we are to pity those who have been forced to swear against their Consciences; so are we to pray, that they will rather reflect upon the Majesty and Dread of God by whom they swore, than upon the iniquity and sin of those persons, who compelled them to it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>